<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Getting started with oXygen</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Information about publication or distribution</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Getting started with oXygen</head>
            <p>In this little tutorial, we will use oXygen to <list>
                  <item>create a new TEI XML document</item>
                  <item>add valid tags to a document</item>
                  <item>validate the document continually</item>
                  <item>display the document in different ways</item>
               </list></p>
            <p rend="box">If you haven't installed oXygen already, download it from <ptr
                  target="http://www.oxygenxml.com/download_oxygenxml_editor.html"/> and use the
               free 30 day trial licence. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>A born-digital document</head>
            <list>
               <item>Start oXygen. and click the <ident>New</ident> icon at top left (or type
                  CTRL-N) to open the New dialogue box</item>
               <item>Type <code>bare</code> in the search box at the top and then press return or
                  click the Create button at the bottom</item>
               <item>oXygen displays the bare bones of a minimal document in its main window and a
                  summary of its structure on the left (if you don't see the Summary view, you can
                  add it by selecting Document -> View -> Summary)</item>
            </list>
            <p><graphic height="5cm" url="../images/nouveau-bare-2.png"/></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Metadata matters</head>
            <p> TEI documents always have a <term>header</term>, which <emph>must</emph> provide
               information about the title, distribution, and source of a digital resource. oXygen
               suggests some text for each of these which you can now modify <list>
                  <item>replace the word <q>Title</q> by a title for your document: up to you to
                     decide, but something like <q>Getting started with oXygen</q> will do</item>
                  <item>Replace the other two text fragments in the same way: for example, for the
                     publication you might put <q>unpublished draft</q> or <q>Distributed on
                        vilnius.obdurodon.org</q> or something similar;</item><item> for the source description
                     we suggest <q>An original work, created at a TEI Workshop</q></item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>oXygen covers your back -1</head>
            <p>oXygen works actively to keep your document well formed and valid. What happens if
               you make an error? <list>
                  <item>delete a few letters from any tag., for example change
                        <gi>publicationStmt</gi> into <gi>publicat</gi>.</item>
                  <item>oXygen does what it can: it changes the end-tag so that it matches the
                     start-tag and the document remains well-formed. </item>
                  <item>But the document is no longer valid: the erroneous tags are underlined in
                     red; there is an error message at the bottom of the screen, and there are red
                     lines on the right of the screen. </item>
                  <item>Click the red line to see the corresponding error message: one error can
                     lead to others</item>
                  <item>Type CTRL-Z to undo your changes and return to a state of grace: the angry
                     red square at top right turns into a jolly green square when you have done
                     so.</item>
               </list></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>oXygen covers your back -2</head>

            <p>oXygen can also help you by proposing tags available in specific locations <list>
                  <item>Put the cursor at the end of the 7th or start of the 8th line</item>
                  <item>Type a <code>&lt;</code> and pause a moment;</item>
                  <item>The green square becomes red because you have not yet supplied an element
                     name</item>
                  <item>oXygen also shows you a ist of the tags you can enter at this point in a
                     valid document: you can for example insert an <gi>author</gi> element, or a
                     second <gi>title</gi>, terminate the <gi>titleStmt</gi>, or add an XML
                     comment</item>
                  <item>Hit the RETURN key to accept the first suggestion. oXygen inserts the start
                     and end tags for a new <gi>author</gi></item>
                  <item>The cursor remains inside the start tag, so that you can add some
                     attributes, but we won't do that for now. Move the cursor one character to the
                     right and type your name as author of the document.</item>
               </list></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Adding content to the document</head>
            <p>A document containing just one paragraph is a bit unlikely! The schema <term>TEI
                  bare</term> allows you to markup the following components of a text : <list>
                  <item>titles .... to be tagged with the <gi>head</gi> element</item>
                  <item>chapters ... to be tagged with the <gi>div</gi> element </item>
                  <item>lists ... to be tagged with the <gi>list</gi> element (which can itself
                     contain <gi>label</gi> or <gi>item</gi> elements) </item>
                  <item>paragraphs ... to be tagged with the <gi>p</gi> element</item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Let's go!</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Adding tags to existing content</head>
            <p>You've already seen how oXygen allows you to insert a new element. Suppose however
               you want to add tagging to text that is already there in the document. Can you do it
               without typing the tags? Of course!</p>
            <p><list>
                  <item>Select the content of the <gi>body</gi> element, that is, the sequemce
                        <code>&lt;p>Some text here&lt;/p></code></item>
                  <item>Type CTRL-E (or select Document-> Markup -> Surround with tags)</item>
                  <item>oXygen gives you a list of tags which can be used at this point: select
                        <gi>div</gi> and click OK or press RETURN</item>
                  <item>This new <gi>div</gi> will contain your first chapter. Give it a title, by
                     inserting a <gi>head</gi> element at its start. </item>
               </list></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Adding attributes</head>
            <p>Now let's give the chapter a number, by using the attribute <att>n</att> which is
               available for any TEI element, including <gi>div</gi>. <list>
                  <item>Put the cursor inside the start-tag for <gi>div</gi> and just before the
                        <code>&gt;</code> ; type a space. oXygen shows a list of available
                     attributes.</item>
                  <item>Hit RETURN to select <att>n</att> : oXygen tells you that you must supply a
                     value for this attribute and the cursor stays inside the quote marks so that
                     you can do so</item>
                  <item>Type (say) <code>1</code> and your document is valid again</item>
               </list></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Get creative!</head>
            <p>Your document should now look like this: </p>
            <p><graphic height="3cm" url="../images/body-shot.png"/></p>
            <p>Now add some text to that paragraph: whatever you feel like writing about ... the
               weather, the political situation, your lunch, your opinion of oXygen so far, whatever
               you like.</p>
            <p>Sooner or later you'll need to close this paragraph and start a new one. You could do
               this by just typing the tags <tag>/p>&lt;p</tag> but there's an easier way </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Element splitting</head>
            <p>Suppose you have hundreds of words in your sole paragraph and you want to split it
               into several <gi>p</gi> elements.<list>
                  <item>Put the cursor at the position where you want to end a paragraph</item>
                  <item>Type ALT-SHIFT-D or select Document -> Markup -> Split element </item>
                  <item>You could do the same thing to split your chapter into two. Take care to
                     put the cursor in the right place though: it must be between two <gi>p</gi>
                     elements, rather than inside one!</item>
                  <item>In your next chapter, why not add a <gi>list</gi> element?</item>
               </list></p>
         </div>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
